A Finding Aid to the Reginald Gammon Papers, 1927-2007, bulk 1960-2005, in the Archives of American Art AAA.gammreg
Archives of American Art
Reginald Gammon papers
bulk 1960-2005
1927-2007
AAA.gammreg
Archives of American Art
2.4 Linear feet
The Reginald Gammon papers measure 2.4 linear feet and date from 1927 to 2007 (bulk 1960-2005). The papers contain biographical material, personal and professional correspondence, writings and artwork by Gammon, printed material, and photographs regarding Gammon's career as a painter, educator, and prominent member of the African American art scene.
Gammon, Reginald, 1921-2005
Scope and Contents note
The Reginald Gammon papers measure 2.4 linear feet and date from 1927 to 2007 (bulk 1960-2005). The papers contain biographical material, personal and professional correspondence, writings and artwork by Gammon, printed material, and photographs regarding Gammon's career as a painter, educator, and prominent member of the African American art scene.
A small selection of biographic information about Gammon includes certificates, military documentation, and interviews. Approximately half of the collection consists of correspondence with other artists, museums, galleries and arts organizations. Correspondence documents his work with a number of African American arts organizations across the country. Of note is correspondence with Benny Andrews, Romare Bearden, Vivian Browne, Thomas Frey, Joseph Greenberg, Patrick King, Hughie Lee-Smith, Harry Overton, and Jonathan Wynberg. Writings by Gammon including personal and lecture notes as well as project drafts. Printed materials consist primarily of exhibition catalogs. Artwork includes pencil and ink sketches, advertisement mock-ups, collages, and paintings. Photographs depict Gammon at school, in the Navy, with other artists friends, and in his studio.
Biographical/Historical note
Reginald A. Gammon (1921-2005) was a painter and art educator, working in New York City, Michigan, and Albuquerque, New Mexico. He was a founding member of Spiral, an African American artist's collective and member of the New Mexico Afro-American Artist Guild. He also taught in the New York public schools and at Western Michigan University.
Gammon was born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to Reginald and Martha Brown Gammon. After graduating high school in 1941, Gammon received a scholarship to study art at the Philadelphia Museum College of Art (then called the Philadelphia Museum School of Industrial Arts). With the arrival of his draft notice, Gammon joined the Navy and served from 1944-1946 with an all-black unit stationed in Guam. After the war he returned to Philadelphia but soon moved to New York where he worked odd jobs to support his work as an artist. It was during this time in New York that he met Janice Goldberger (Jonni), whom he married in 1972.
In 1963, Gammon joined the Spiral, a group of African American artists that included Romare Bearden, Richard Mayhew, Hale Woodruff, and Alvin Hollingsworth. While a member of this group, Gammon participated in the "Black and White" exhibition at the Christopher Street Gallery. After Spiral disbanded, Gammon formed the Black Emergency Cultural Coalition with Benny Andrews. This highly political group of artists picketed the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Whitney Museum of Modern Art to protest the exclusion of black artists and curators.
Around this same time, Gammon received a position with New York Public Schools, where he taught in the Saturday Academy Program. This program allowed children from Harlem to work with resident artists. While in this position, Gammon was recommended by Hughie Lee-Smith for a visiting lectureship at Western Michigan University. The 10-day lectureship was quickly extended into a one-semester contract. Gammon remained in this position for 21 years, finally retiring in 1991 as Full Professor Emeritus of Fine Arts and Humanities.
After leaving Michigan, Gammon settled in Albuquerque, New Mexico in 1992. Gammon became involved in civic organizations such as the New Mexico Afro-American Artist Guild and the Albuquerque United Artists. In addition to artist groups, Gammon was the artist-in-residence from 1992-2005 at the Harwood Art Center where he had a painting studio. In 1996 Gammon co-founded the New Grounds Print Workshop where he developed his final body of work, a collection of over 100 historically important prints of jazz musicians and gospel singers.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1936-2006 (0.2 linear feet, Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1964-2005 (0.8 linear feet, Box 1-3)
Series 3: Writings and Notebooks, circa 1980s (0.2 linear feet, Box 2)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1955-2005 (0.4 linear feet, Box 2, OV 4)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1927-2003 (0.2 linear feet, Box 2-3)
Series 6: Artwork, 1960s-2007 (0.5 linear feet, Box 2-3, Artifact)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2007 and 2008 by Janice Gammon, Gammon's widow.
Bearden, Romare, 1911-1988; Benny Andrews, 1930-2006; Browne, Vivian E., 1929-1993; Fray, Thomas; Greenberg, Joseph J., 1915-1991; King, Patrick; Lee-Smith, Hughie; Overton, Harry; Wynberg, Jonathan; African American artists--New Mexico--Albuquerque; Art teachers--New Mexico--Albuquerque; Art--Study and teaching; Artists' studios--Photographs; Collages; Interviews; Painters--New Mexico--Albuquerque; Paintings; Photographs; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1936-2006; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include Gammon's school records, teaching certifications, official draft notice and his certificate of honorable discharge. The series also includes a number of digital and sound recordings of interviews, home videos, and documentary recordings made about Gammon's career. Other items of interest in this series are obituaries and documents from a variety of memorial services.
  - Life Documents, 1936-1946; 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1949-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Teaching Certification, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Navy Records, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal Business Records, 1979-2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interview Requests, 1999; 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Home Videos & Interviews, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes 1 electronic disk (DVD): "Part 1: Reggie at DePeaux's House," "Part 2: Two Advertisements," "Part 3: Seagram's Interview"
  - Interview for Hatch-Billips, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes 1 elctronic disk (CD).
  - Interviews, 1970s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes 1 electronic disk (DVD): "Part 1: TV interview 'Fade to Black'" "Part 2: Black & White version of 'REGGIE' followed by discussion group" "Part 3: Color version of 'REGGIE'"
  - Interview Sponsored by Seagram's Gin, 1996; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorial Services, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Obituaries, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1964-2005; Series 2; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Correspondence with other artists, many of whom were Gammon's students, include Benny Andrews, Romare Bearden, Vivian Browne, Thomas Frey, Joseph Greenberg, Patrick King, Hughie Lee-Smith, Harry Overton, and Jonathan Wynberg. Also found are letters with various museums, galleries and arts organizations including Howard University, the LewAllen Gallery, Midtown Galleries, The Spiral Group, the Smithsonian Institution Anacostia Museum and several African American arts organizations. Topics from these letters range from personal daily life to lectures requests to exhibition solicitations. A specific file of note in this series is the correspondence concerning Gammon's only international exhibition in Rodez, France.
  - ACI Films, Inc., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Acts of Art, Inc., 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Albuquerque Festival of the Arts, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Andrews, Benny, 1971; 1992-2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Art Center of Battle Creek, 1992-1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - A, Miscellaneous, 1970-2005 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Backus, Rob, 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bearden, Romare H., 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brandywine Workshop, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Browne, Vivian E., 1989-1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Burrows, Vinie, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - B, Miscellaneous, 1989-2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Clark, Alice, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cue, Carter, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - C, Miscellaneous, 1970-1978; 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - de Peaux, Richard, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - D, Miscellaneous, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - E, Miscellaneous, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - France, regarding Exhibition, 1993-2003 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Freedom Ways, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Frey, Thomas, 1978-2005 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 1964-1971; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gammon, Corey, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Greenberg, Joseph, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Greeting Cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 2000; 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hampton University Museum, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Harper & Row Publishers, Inc., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Henderson, Harry, 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Hitchcock, Scott, 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Hochstein, Rolaine, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Howard University, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - H-I, Miscellaneous, 1973-1974; 1990s (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - J, Miscellaneous, 1972-1975; 1996 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - King, Patrick, 1992-2005; 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1971-1998 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Lee-Smith, Hughie and Patricia, 1995-1996; 1971 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - LewAllen Gallery, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1970-2005 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Malcolm X College, circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Mangione, Pat, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Midtown Galleries, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Miller, Earl, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Moore, Lewis Tanner, 1995-2001 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Museum of African American Art, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - National Afro-American Museum & Cultural Center, 1991-2005 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - National Conference of Artists, 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - National Gallery of Art, 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - New Mexico African American Artists Guild, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - N, Miscellaneous, 1972-1999 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Overton, Harvey, 1985-2005 (Box 1, Folder 69-71)
  - O, Miscellaneous, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Poui Art Gallery, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Proctor, Lee H., 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Provancher, John and Judy, 1992-2000 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - P, Miscellaneous, 1969-2005 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - R, Miscellaneous, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - School District of Philadelphia, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Schomberg Center for Reseach in Black Culture, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Smithsonian Institution, Anacostia Museum, 1998-2003 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - The Spiral Group, 1988-2000 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Swerdolf, Daniel, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - S, Miscellaneous, 1993-2005; 1975 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - T, Miscellaneous, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Unidentifiable, 1970-2005 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Western Michigan University, 1996; 1969-1986 (Box 1, Folder 86-87)
  - U, Miscellaneous, 1969-2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - W, Miscellaneous, 1970-2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Oversized material housed in Box 3.
  - Y, Miscellaneous, 1976-2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oversize Wynberg, Jonathan, 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Illustrated Letter.
- Writings and Notebooks, circa 1980s; Series 3; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Found here are lecture notes as well as a sound recording of a lecture given at Western Michigan University on "Black Artists from the Harlem Renaissance to the Present." In addition to Gammon's academic work, this series contains draft grant proposals and the first draft of a research proposal on "The Tattoo as Non-verbal Communication." Also of interest is a notebook of draft handwritten letters.
  - Lecture, "Black Artists from the Harlem Renaissance to the Present", 1980s; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lecture Notes, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Grant Proposals, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Personal Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Personal Notebook, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letter Notebooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Address Notebook, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, 1955-2005; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2, OV 4
  The printed material primarily consists of exhibition catalogs and announcements, including the catalog "Ida y vuelta" which documents Gammon's 1998 exhibition in Rodez, France. Other materials found in this series are published illustrations and newspaper clippings that feature Gammon and his work. Two small examples of source material Gammon used for teaching and painting can also be found.
  - Art, A History, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Articles and Newsletters, 1976-2005 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1971-2004 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Afro-American Artists, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Exhibition Catalog, African American Artists, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Catalog, The International Review of African American Art, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Catalog, African American Artists II, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Anacostia Museum, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Ben Nicholson, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Contemporary Black Artists, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Mercury Gallery, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Catalog, National Arts Club, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Catalog, New York Cultural Center, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Ohio University, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Rackstraw Downes, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Reginald Marsh, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Exhibition Catalog, Rodez, France, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hugo Gellert, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Published Illustrations, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - New Orleans Art Review, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Source Material, Boxing, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Source Material, Jazz, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Western Michigan University, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Oversize Poster, circa 1988 (Box OV 4)
- Photographic Material, 1927-2003; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Found here are photograph portraits of Gammon, and photographs depicting Gammon in school, in the Navy, and family and friends in Philadelphia. More recent photos show Gammon with other artists friends and in his painting studio.
  - Portraits of Reginald Gammon, 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Snapshots of Reginald Gammon, 1931; 1968-1994 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Navy Photographs, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Photographs with Janice Gammon, 1949-1991 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Family Photographs, 1927-1980s (Box 2, Folder 41-43)
  - Photographs with Friends, 1970-2001 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Photographs of Gammon in Studio, 2003; 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Kalamazoo Institute of Art Photographs, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Oversize Class Photographs, 1936; 1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Artwork, 1960s-2007; Series 6; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2-3, Artifact
  The Art work series is a varied and extensive sampling of Gammon's work. Mediums included in this series range from pencil sketches to fully completed and framed paintings. Some of his preliminary works show examples of Gammon's use of color and collage. The series also contains published work such as commercial posters and storyboards for children's books, as well as mock-ups for advertisements.
  - Black & White Storyboard, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Ink Drawings, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Marker Sketches, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Paint Sketches, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Pencil Sketches, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Print Mockups, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 53-57)
  - Digital Copies of Art Work, 2007; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Storyboard, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Oversize Collage, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Oversize Ink Drawings from box2, folder 48, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Oversize Marker Sketches from box 2, folder 49, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Paintings, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Pencil Sketches from box 2, folder 52, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Oversize Print Mockups from box 2, folder 53-57, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Oversize Print Posters, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Oversize Storyboard from box 2, folder 59, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 10-13)
  - Framed Acrylic Painting, 1960s-1990s (Box Artifact)